We ask a lot of questions
about our diet.
What’s the right way to
treat a chronic illness?
Fight off a virus,
lose weight?
The problem is, we get
a lot of different answers.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Did you know that if you
buy vitamin E supplements
you may in fact be paying
to live a shorter life?
Here’s our first story.
Randomized controlled trials
show that daily
vitamin D supplementation
appears to reduce the risk
of acute respiratory infections
in children and adolescents,
but it does not seem
to make a difference in adults,
nor does D appear effective
for boosting
antibody responses
to influenza vaccination.
What about vitamin E?
Most places, you'll read
that there are eight different
tocopherols and tocotrienols
that are collectively known
as vitamin E,
but only alpha-tocopherol
has been shown
to protect against
human vitamin E deficiency.
So alpha-tocopherol
is the only bona fide vitamin E
and is the one found
in vitamin E supplements.
There are observational data
suggesting
those self-reporting
supplementation with vitamin E
have, for example,
better pneumonia outcomes,
but only interventional trials
can prove if this is the case.
Compared to placebo supplements,
vitamin E was able
to significantly boost immunity
to hepatitis B
and tetanus vaccinations
(though not to diphtheria
or pneumonia).
One randomized controlled trial
found that vitamin E
supplementation of the elderly
did not cut down on lower
respiratory tract infections
(like pneumonia)
but did reduce the incidence
of upper respiratory tract
infections
(like the common cold)
by about 20 percent
over one year.
But another study
using the same dose
found no preventive benefit,
and vitamin E supplementation
actually made the infections
they did get even worse,
with a greater number
and severity of symptoms,
including a greater likelihood
of fever
and activity restriction.
By far the largest study
on vitamin E
and respiratory infections
was the ATBC Study
that randomized
nearly 15,000 smokers
to vitamin E or placebo
for about 5 years.
No overall effect
was found either way
between the vitamin E
and placebo groups,
but upon subgroup analysis
it appeared
that while lighter smokers
living in cities
appeared to benefit
with about a 50 percent
lower risk
of catching the common cold,
vitamin E appeared
to be a detriment
to heavier smokers
living outside of cities,
resulting in about a 50 percent
increased risk.
"Accordingly,"
concluded the investigators,
"caution should be maintained
in public health
recommendations
on vitamin E supplementation
until its effects
are better understood."
The pneumonia results
from the same study
took a similar turn.
No overall effect of vitamin E
compared to placebo,
but upon further analysis,
vitamin E appeared
to decrease pneumonia risk
among lighter smokers
who exercised,
yet increased pneumonia risk
among heavier smokers
who did not.
Higher pneumonia rates
were also noted
in those randomized
to vitamin D
and were either low
or high body weight,
but only, apparently,
among those
with higher dietary
vitamin C intake.
Heavy smokers
who got a lot of C
also seemed to have
higher tuberculosis rates on E
compared to placebo.
This kind of slicing
and dicing of data
is frowned upon, as it can
spawn spurious connections,
so these findings are regarded
only as exploratory
for further
research directions.
Overall mortality
in the ATBC Study was similar
between the vitamin E
and placebo groups,
though again
there were subgroups
that appeared to have
their lives either cut short
or extended.
There have been dozens
of controlled clinical trials
on vitamin E,
and most meta-analyses
found a small
but apparent real increase
in the risk of mortality
among those randomized
to vitamin E.
In other words, those who buy
vitamin E supplements
may be, in effect, paying
to live a shorter life.
Across 46 trials,
12 percent died
in the vitamin E groups
versus about 10 percent
in the placebo groups.
This is similar to the increase
in mortality
seen with beta carotene
supplementation-
approximately 14 percent
versus 11 percent
across 26 randomized trials.
The goal of the ATBC
was to see if taking
antioxidant supplements
like vitamin E or beta carotene
could help prevent lung cancer
in smokers.
Vitamin E had no effect
on lung cancer,
and beta-carotene unexpectedly
actually increased
lung cancer rates,
but vitamin E did,
incidentally,
appear to reduce
incident prostate cancer rates.
This helped inspire
the SELECT study,
the largest cancer
prevention trial ever performed.
More than 35,000 men were
randomized to take vitamin E,
selenium, both,
or neither (just placebos).
The selenium
didn't appear to matter,
but those randomized
to the straight vitamin E group
ended up with a 17 percent
greater risk
of developing prostate cancer.
If 100 men took vitamin E
for a decade,
we would expect to see
one or two of them
to be diagnosed
with prostate cancer
that they otherwise
wouldn't have gotten
had they wasted their money
on sugar pills instead.
Can vitamin E or selenium supplements
prevent or treat Alzheimer's?
Here are some answers.
Oxidative stress
from free radicals
is the one of the pathways
implicated in the development
and deterioration
of Alzheimer's brains,
given the evidence of excess
oxidative DNA damage on autopsy.
So, what about trying
an antioxidant?
Vitamin E levels
tend to be lower
in the bloodstreams of those
with cognitive impairment
or dementia,
but which came first?
Maybe Alzheimer's disease
led to poor eating,
rather than poor eating
leading to Alzheimer's disease.
Greater vitamin E intake
from foods
is clearly associated
with a lower risk
of developing Alzheimer's,
but greater vitamin E intake
from supplements is not.
But, that didn't stop
researchers
from including a vitamin E arm
in the largest primary
prevention study
of Alzheimer's disease to date.
The Prevention
of Alzheimer's Disease
by Vitamin E and Selenium trial
randomized more than
7500 older men
to take vitamin E, selenium,
both, or neither-just placebos-
for five years.
To quote from the conclusion:
"Neither supplement
prevented dementia."
A separate long-term vitamin E
supplementation trial
of older women similarly found
no protection
against cognitive decline.
Neither did vitamin E
appear to benefit those
with mild cognitive impairment,
but the trials on Alzheimer's
patients themselves
started to get more interesting.
The first trial,
published in the New England
Journal of Medicine,
randomized more than 150
Alzheimer's patients
to vitamin E or placebo
to see if vitamin E could slow
the progression of the disease.
The primary outcome
was the number of days
until of one of any
of the following happened:
death, institutionalization,
loss of the ability
to perform basic activities
of daily living,
or sliding into severe dementia,
where you suffer
a complete loss
of sense of time or place.
On first analysis,
vitamin E flopped:
no significant slowing
of progression.
Digging deeper,
the researchers realized
that despite
the random allotment,
the placebo group
just by chance
ended up with patients
with milder disease.
After taking that into account,
the difference in outcomes
between the vitamin E
and placebo groups
widened substantially.
Now, this kind of
unplanned post-hoc analysis
is heavily frowned upon,
but the effect
seemed so sizable
they went ahead
and published it.
In the placebo group,
the adjusted time to death
or loss of independence
was 440 days,
but in the vitamin E group,
after the baseline cognition
was normalized,
it was 670 days,
more than seven months later.
However,
given the unorthodox analysis,
the scientific world waited
for the study to be replicated.
And here we go:
more than 600 patients
with mild to moderate
Alzheimer's disease
were subsequently randomized
to vitamin E supplements,
the drug memantine, both,
or neither (just placebos)
for two years.
Although there was no slowing
of cognitive decline
after adjusting
for multiple comparisons,
there was a slowing
of functional decline,
in terms of managing
daily activities
like bathing or dressing.
The vitamin E group
appeared to only suffer
about 1.5 years
of functional deterioration
in the two years' time,
resulting in approximately
two hours less caregiver time
required each day
compared to the drug group.
If those were the only two
clinical vitamin E trials,
I would give vitamin E
serious consideration
for those
with Alzheimer's disease.
But, there's a third,
a six-month trial,
that suggested vitamin E
may be detrimental
to cognition
in some Alzheimer's patients.
Obviously, more research
needs to be done.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you hear about any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
I also wrote a
mini book on Ozempic.
Available in softcover,
e-book, and audio versions.
Check it out on NutritionFacts.org.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.